<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Saynt Nycholas of tolle[n]tyne</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1525</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104420</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840158</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840158</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08190)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4632)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 138:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Saynt Nycholas of tolle[n]tyne</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete at the sygne of the sonne by Wynkyn de worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1525?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nicholas, --  of Tolentino, Saint, 1245-1305.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:4632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Saynt Nycholas of tolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyne</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Saint Nicholas of Tolentino</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="holiday">
            <pb facs="tcp:4632:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Saint Nicholas of Tolentino</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4632:2"/>
            <div n="1" type="reading">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His gloryous and bleſſyd confeſſour &amp; true relygyous keper called ſaynt Nycholas
of tollentyne / was borne in a countree called Pycen in a well dyſpoſed Cyte called Fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane.
His fathers name was Compagnous. His mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hyght Amata / bothe were very deuoute folke / and well
dyſpoſed. The whiche longe lackynge a chylde gretely deſyrynge to haue one / full beſyly
bothe daye &amp; nyght beſoughte almyghty god with deuoute voyce &amp; prayers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myghte
haue one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myght be his dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And bycauſe they thought themſelfe vn worthy
to be herde / they dayly worſhipped bleſſyd ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Nycholas deuoutly beſechynge hym to be
theyr aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght obteyne theyr petycionand aſkynge. And at the laſte of theyr
more deuocyon by the inſpyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the holy ghoſt they wente on pylgrymage to a towne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree of Apuley called Barus. Where the for ſayd gloryous byſſhop ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Nycholas by an
ymage y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was there of hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was gretely ſought &amp; worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. And whan they had done
theyr pylgry mage they retourned home agayne faythefully truſtynge on god our lady &amp; ſaynt
Nycholas to haue theyr deſyrynge &amp; petycyon / as at the laſte they had by theyr
conceſſyon &amp; grace. For anone after they came home y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forſayd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Amata
conceyued and by proceſſe ſhe had a chylde / whome ſhe cauſed to be cryſtened Nycholas
in the worſhyp of theyr aduocate &amp; patron ſaynt Nycho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>las that they behette to for a
chylde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reading">
               <head>lectio. ij.</head>
               <p>THis forſayd chylde Nycholas brought vp in the vertuous examples &amp; holſome techinges of
his father &amp; mother / &amp; alſo well lettered in ſcrypture / grewe in chyldhode
meruaylouſly good / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the folke of the
<pb facs="tcp:4632:3"/>towne prayſed his vertuous lyuynge bey<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge but a chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / &amp; his gracyous
dyſpoſycyon ayenſt all men / as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyenge afore / ſayd playnly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete holynes
ſholde proue afterwarde in hym / for his lyfe ſhewed and appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a certayne ſpecyall
prerogatyue of all gentylneſſe certely / mekenes / ſoftenes / chaſtyte of mynde and body
and ſo grete abſtynence he dyde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was but .vij. yere olde he faſted thre dayes in
the weke. Alſo he was of gret pyte / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oftentymes wylfully he brought pore men ſeke or
dyſeaſed in to his fathers houſe / and there through his entyſe cauſed them to be releued
&amp; cheryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Alſo he was of good relygyon and byleue vnto god whoſe enſamples he
loked vpon or redde or elles reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good wordes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ryght
fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſyre he gladly herde &amp; faſtly euer prynted them in his mynde. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche
thynge is noted a meruayll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche bleſſed Nycholas tolde in his laſte dayes to a certayne
relygous man that toke hede to hym whan he was ſore ſeke on a tyme / ſaynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in his
chyldehode whan he dyde helpe a preeſt to ſynge maſſe. Whan the bleſſed ſacrament was
lyfte vp / our ſauyour Ieſu cryſt appered to hym in the lykenes of a fayre chylde in a
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucent garmente and a bryght ſhynynge face and mery chere / ſaynt Nycholas herde hym ſayng
theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>Innocentes &amp; recti adheſerunt michi. That is to ſaye Innocentes &amp; good harmeles men
hath drawen vnto me. Alſo he ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſo moche that he ſtrongely relyſted theyr grete
temptacyon of all gooſtly enmyes &amp; euer for ſoke his owne wyl to pleaſe hym / he ſholde
haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more grace and accepcyon of prayers. Lo what mede it is to waxe good by tymes / for grace
groweth after gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reading">
               <head>Lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:4632:3"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S he was a yonge man he gretely coueyted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygyon / whiche euer he ſpecyally loued / &amp;
was made a chanon in a place called ſaynt ſauyour / he grew vp in vertue as he begon tredynge
downe &amp; leuynge a ſyde all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyces of youth &amp; with grete payne merueyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly for
berynge and leuynge all maner of ſlouth wyld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of youth. It forturied on a tyme
he herde a certayne relygyous man of the nombre of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſaynt Auſtyn had
ordeyned &amp; called frere heremyte whan this bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas herde this holy rely
gyous man declare &amp; ſhewe openly amonge the people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perylles / Ieoperdyes &amp; vanytees
of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde exorty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge all folke in theyr hertes to dyſpyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / &amp; whan this
bleſſed Nycholas herde hym anone it kyndeled hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inwardly / in ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vtterly he
purpoſed wylfully to do &amp; fullfyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thynge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his herte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the relygyous man had
aduyſed hym to do. Wherfore he yode to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygyous man whoſe wordes were roted in his herte
&amp; lowly prayed hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde helpe hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for charyte out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bandes of the worlde in the
whiche ſayd ſaynt Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas I haue ben fetered &amp; combred vnto this daye / &amp; that I
myght be worthy too be receyued amonge the nombre of your bretherne freres hermytes of the ordre of
ſaynt Auſtyn. For I quod ſaynt Nycholas hertely deſyre euer to ſerue &amp; gyue me to god
/ vtterly to for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuyl / &amp; my fleſſhe. And in euery thynge &amp;
poynt to lyue relygyouſly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermeſt of my power by the grace of god / &amp; ſo dyde he
gladly. His father and his mother were gladde thereof / and at the fyrſt conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiij.</head>
               <p>AS this bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> upon hym the relygion of frere hermytes of the
ordre
<pb facs="tcp:4632:4"/>of ſaynt Auſtyn aboute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xv. yere of his age / helyued vertuouſly therin tyll
conuenyent &amp; able tyme of his ful aege / and than he was made a preeſt in a towne called
cy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gulꝰ. At y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſte he was ſente of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rulers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordre to Tollentyne where he ledde
almooſt all his lyfe with a merueylous abſtyne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in ſo moche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he faſted .iiij. day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es
euery weke brede &amp; water alonely / beſyde the dayes that were commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the chyrche.
Alſo fleſſhe / fyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe nor egges / whyte mete nor apples this bleſſed Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas neuer
ete. And on a tyme whan he was ſore ſeke they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had power to commaunde vnneth coude brynge
hym or cauſe him to ete fleſſ he a certayne ſeaſon bycau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to make hym ſtronge and
reſtore his helthe. And an other tyme whan he was ſo ſore &amp; greuouſly ſeke than there
ſemed no lenger lyfe in hym / nor no man behete hym lyfe in this worlde / as he was in a faynt
ſlepe he ſawe Mary vyrgyn mother of god / &amp; alſo ſaynt Auſtyn whoſe helpe he
beſought w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all entencyon of all his her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſtandynge by hym w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> a mery chere. And whan this
bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas ſawe them afore hym he gretly meruaylled and thanked them of theyr
comynge. And they exorted hym &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded hym to be of good chere / the bleſſed vyrgyn
Mary ſhewed her fynger to a ſtrete and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the name of her ſone he ſholde
go in that ſtrete to a certayne woman whoſe name ſhe ſhewed hym / &amp; that he ſholde
aſke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> woman newe bake brede in the honoure of our lady &amp; her ſone and wete it in water / 
and anone he ſholde amende. And as he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in his ſlepe he dyde wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he waked
truſty<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in almyghty god &amp; the bleſſed vyrgyn mary and ſaynt Auſtyn to be heled / 
&amp; ſo he was.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:4632:4"/>
               <p>THis bleſſyd ſaynt Nycholas punyſſhed his fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe &amp; his body with grete
hardnes &amp; correccyon And for more correccyon he ware mooſt often chaynes of yron. And alſo
ſofte &amp; eaſy beddes &amp; ſyttynges &amp; ſofte and eaſy clothes &amp; raymentes he
euer refuſed. He laye vpon chaffe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche he thoughte was to eaſy for his body. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
clothes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ware was ſharpe courſe and harde and often chafed his body in many places.
Alſo in hym was grete ſtedfaſtnes / for on a tyme whan he was entyſed &amp; counſaylled
of a certayne ryche kynneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde leue ſo ſharpe &amp; harde a lyfe and
go backe to an other place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he coude gete him to where he myght lyue more plenteouſly / and
more delycyouſly ſaynt Nycholas euer refuſed it vtterly with a ſtronge mynde in god / for
he coude neuer bowe his mynde ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. His mekenes &amp; obedyence was excedynge without meſure / 
for not alonely to his ſuperyour / but alſo to his euenall and his inferyor. He was obedyent in
goodnes and ſuffred them all. He had to all folke a ſynguler and a meruaylous pyte and charyte
/ namely to poore folke / and nedy / &amp; to theym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were in ony trouble or ſekenes / whome
often he vyſyted &amp; conforted whan he was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeke and weyke hymſelfe. Somtyme he
comforted them &amp; releued them with wordes and ſomtyme he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted theym to kepe pacyence
with good doctryne of ſcrypture. And ſomtyme he refreſſhed theym with bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely fode and
clothynge euery man after his nede. Alſo he cauſed thrughe his ſwete exortacyon and grete
dyly gence many men that he knewe had rycheſſe to do the ſame too the poore and nedy. Whan
this bleſſed ſaynte Nycholas had knowledge of ony folkes ſynnes or fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes eyther by preuy
confeſſyon / or by ony otherwyſe he
<pb facs="tcp:4632:5"/>was ſo ſory that he wolde wepe and praye for them and punyſſhed his body ſore
with faſtes and correccyon to gete them forgyuenes and grace to amende themſelfe and to
contynue in goodnes. This bleſſed ſaynt Nycho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>las was pale of face ſhamefaſt and gladde / 
and mery of countenaunce / of a ſmothe and fayre fleſſhe / and kynde to euery body. And he
was mooſt myſe / redy / and dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente to ony thynge that he ſholde do that was good &amp;
goodly</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reading">
               <head>Lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .vi.</head>
               <p>ALſo this bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas ſayd maſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery daye / but he neuer ſayd
maſſe but he was clene ſhryuen afore / ne there can no tongue tell the deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon that he had
euer and in eſpecyall at maſſe / for the ſtreyght of his maſſe was ſo ſpedy
towardes god that on a tyme whan he wente to a place called Pethaurus in a certayne wylderneſſe
by the waye and layde hym downe vpon the grounde for fayntnes / and was halfe a ſlepe there
appered vnto hym the ſoule of a certayne man whome ſaynt Nycholas knewe well ynoghe and loued
in his lyfe / the whiche prayed hym inſtauntly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde ſaye maſſe for hym / the whiche
ſholde not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer and do profyte alonely to hym but alſo it ſholde profyte vnto innumerable
other ſoules the whiche ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les were in a certayne playne there nye by that he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed to
ſaynt Nycholas / where they were punyſſhed and tormented with greuous paynes / and that
ſame ſoule the whiche was comen vnto ſaynt Nycholas for ſocoure and helpe was alſo
tormented with them with the ſame ſelfe tormentes that they hadde. And euen ſo it was done.
¶ For ſeuen dayes after this bleſſed ſaynt
<pb facs="tcp:4632:5"/>Nycholas had done the maſſe he ſawe than in his ſlepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſoule in
grete &amp; infynyte Ioy and myrthe than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge ſaynt Nycholas entyerly beſechynge hym that
thrughe his helpe the other grete innumerable multy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſoules myght be delyuered from theyr
greuous paynes / and that they myght come to heuen to euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge Ioye and gladneſſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="holiday">
            <head>Feria. ij.</head>
            <div n="1" type="reading">
               <head>lec. j.</head>
               <p>THe cuſtome of ſyngynge of this bleſſed ſaynte was euer to be beſy ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he
ſlepte neuer a nyght almoſt / but prayed contynually / and the daye alſo / ſaue wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was
beſy eyther in refreſſhynge his body with mete or drynke / the whiche he toke full ſoberly
and full ſeldome as it is ſhewed before / or elles in herynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyons or doyenge other
neceſſary thynges that were good and vertuous. He prayed with ſo grete ſtedfaſtnes and
entencyon &amp; was eleuate &amp; fyrmly ſet with ſo grete attendement &amp; vehemente of
deuocyon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſemed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lely rauyſſhed in god / &amp; vtterly delyuered &amp; done of fro
man / nor there was nothynge ſo hygh and grete to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne but with the excelente delyte &amp;
beſynes as who ſayth with ſoo hote affeccyon &amp; hyghe deuocyan of his mooſt ſtedfaſt
prayers this bleſſed ſaynt obteyned it &amp; gate it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .ij.</head>
               <p>FOr y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche namely he vſed a certayne oratory &amp; praynge place Ioyned &amp; faſt by an
aulter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nowe his mooſt holy bones are &amp; reſt. Alſo in his celle laye a ſtone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
whiche he kneled vpon / &amp; another y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his armes vpon whan he was ſo wery y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he
coude
<pb facs="tcp:4632:6"/>in no wyſe holde theym vp no lenger / and wynter and ſomer kneeled on the colde
ſtones.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reading">
               <head>lectio. iij.</head>
               <p>HErof the fendes had grete dyſpyte ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ceſed not alonely to tempte hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyuers
temptacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / but alſo they ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they coude in no wyſe cauſe hym to conſente to no
maner ſuggeſtyons of temptacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / ſette agaynſte hym open bataylle / and vexed hym with
mooſt ſharpeſt rebukes / threttes vexacyons and ſore woundes. More ouer more Inwardly and
hardly than a man can thynke. ¶ And more ouer on a tyme whan this bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas
amended his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes the deuylles toke it awaye frome hym bycauſe his prayer was of ſoo grete
effecte / &amp; they wolde haue cauſed hym to leue of his prayer / and muſe on thynges
vnprofytable to his ſoule the whiche this bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas knewe ryght well bycauſe
of his good lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge &amp; mooſte grete payne in reſyſtynge temptacyon the whiche two thynges
good lyuinge and forſakynge the conſentynge of temptacion &amp; for the ſame cauſe another
tyme they put out his lampe &amp; caſt it on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grounde and brake it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiij.</head>
               <p>ALſo oftentymes theſe forſayde deuylles made grete noyſes in his celle houlynge
abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly / bycauſe his prayers was of ſo grete effecte / &amp; made ruſſhynge &amp;
claterynge of ſtones / and crackynge of the tymbre as all the celle ſhold haue fallen downe.
And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all this they ſeynge that they coude not in no wyſe let hym of his prayer / nor ones
too make hym to loke aſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:4632:6"/>for he thought on god. And ones he ſayd yf it be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon I wyll praye moche more
to haue grace to with ſtande it. yf it be goddes ſonde I wyll praye feruentely to haue mercy
and grace for I care not what payne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to my body ſo it be to the helthe of my ſoule. And
the deuylles ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they coude not let hym but he prayed more and more / they came in at his
dore with huge and oryble lokes &amp; ferefull noyſes / rorynges and cryenges. And they ſcorged
hym ſo gretely &amp; bette hym ſo fyerſly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many days after the markes of the whyppes &amp;
ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges appered in all the partes of his body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reading">
               <head>Lectio. v.</head>
               <p>THe whiche alſo another tyme they dydde vnto hym in his celle dore where they mette hym by
nyght goynge to his oratory / they chydde hym &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threwe hym greuouſly to the grounde. And
euer whan he wolde haue ryſen vp they bete hym downe agayne and hurte him ryght ſore / and made
ſo grete noyſe that the freres herde it and roſe from theyr beddes. And as they knewe the
horryble batayle of this holy man they toke hym vp as deed and bare hym too his bedde. And therof
this bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas was ſoo feblyſſhed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer after he was lame. And lyke
wyſe we rede that it happened ſoo to ſaynt Anthony abbot. This thynge was of gret proue &amp;
holynes / &amp; that he was good whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the deuylles hated ſo / &amp; dyde ſo grete payne and
per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecucyon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was a martyr ghoſtly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reading">
               <head>lectio. vi.</head>
               <p>THeſe wycked deuylles alſo had greate enuy of ſaynt Nycholas good bretherne &amp; of the
bryght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:4632:7"/>of his mooſt holy lyfe / fro whome as they knewe wel came ſo bryght bemes of vertue
that chaſed all der<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes of deedly ſynne and lyghtynge with good enſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / and gloryfyed
all holy chyrche bothe ferre &amp; brode. Alſo thrughe the grete counſayll of god it fortuned
that this bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas ſawe a meruaylous vyſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſtarre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte
appered vnto hym whan he was a ſlepe as there were a grete multytude of people vpon it ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought it ſtratched fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne that he was borne in / vnto Tollentyne where after he
deſeaſed. At laſte it appered vnto hym more oftener / whan he was awaked &amp; euer it wente
afore hym to an aulter that ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de by his oratory y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he prayed in.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="holiday">
            <head>Feria. iij.</head>
            <div n="1" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. j.</head>
               <p>WHan this bleſſed ſaynte Nycholas turned his backe to go fro the aulter the ſtarre
vanyſſhed away / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche whan this vertuous father vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtode many yeres afore his dethe
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his body ſholde be buryed there whan he ſhall departe and that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſholde
take it fro thens. Alſo by this vyſyon playnly god wolde it ſholde be ſygnyfied that the
mooſt bryghteſt clerenes of his mooſt holy lyfe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his grete deſerues
ſhewed eueuery where &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ful conſtaunt &amp; ſhyninge bryghtnes of his grete and
innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable myracles ſholde lyghten &amp; ſprynge out at the aulter where by the vyſyon of
god wolde he ſholde be buryed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reading">
               <p>HEre ſhall be ſhewed the myracles of this bleſſed ſay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bryefly. There was a certayn
woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe conceyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chylde was borne or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme / &amp; ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:4632:7"/>toke grete ſorowe &amp; confeſſed herſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete waylyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; wepynges
/ &amp; betoke herſelfe to hym do what he wolde with her / mekely beſechynge hym too praye for
her / for it was vtterly agay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt her wyl. And this blyſſed ſaynt Nycholas ſoo prayed for
her vnto god that euer after ſhe had good delyueraunce. ¶ The ſame woman had a lytyll
doughter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had ſo greuous a ſwellynge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her chy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it muſt nedes be cut &amp; not
without gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te peryll. And yet this blyſſed ſaynt Nycholas thrughe his prayer yelded her
ſafe &amp; ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to her mother.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reading">
               <head>lco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iij.</head>
               <p>ALſo this blyſſed ſaynt Nycholas delyuered an other woman y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche thrughe trauayll
.viij. dayes tofore was greuouſly payned vnto dethe. Alſo he heeled another woman fro grete
payne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe had in her eyen &amp; in her heed &amp; in her face ſwellynge / thrughe the
beſechynge of her ſone to ſaynt Nycholas y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knewe than his vertue. Alſo another chylde
that fel in the fyre &amp; the handes &amp; the armes was ſo ſore bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
grewe togyder / whiche was heeled thrughe the prayers of ſaynt Nycholas.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiij.</head>
               <p>IN lykewyſe he heled another womans ſone that fell alſo in to the fyre &amp; brent all his
face &amp; loſt his ſyght. And alſo he gaue another woman her ſight that had two grete eyen
&amp; they ſtared out and yet ſhe coude not ſe. Alſo another woman had ſo grete
diſeaſe in her eyen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe coude not ſe at all. And ſhe had bothe leches and charmes for
the ſame cauſe / and whan they hadde done the beſte that they coude ſhe was neuer the
better
<pb facs="tcp:4632:8"/>but had more ſorowe / for ſhe loſt bothe her wytte &amp; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſtrengthe / 
but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers of this bleſſyd ſaynt Nycholas ſhe had perfyte ſyght and
ſtrength.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v.</head>
               <p>ALſo it is to be noted that he perfytely heeled an other woman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſo often vexed with
ſo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te need ache y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe myght nother heere nor ſe. ¶ Alſo he perfytely heled a
woman of the blody flyxe / whome no leche nor medycyne coude helpe. Alſo he perfytely heled a
womans breſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was ſore hurte. Alſo he fully heled a certayne relygyous man of his ordre
y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was bruſten &amp; ſore vexed withall. Alſo he heled perfytely another y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had loſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſtrength of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lefte ſyde of his body / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fote of his lefte ſyde. And alſo
another that was mooſt greuouſly vexed with heed ache &amp; many other he dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered fro
mooſt greuous and ferefull axes. Alſo he fully heled another man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hewed blockes &amp; cut
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhynnes of his legges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo grete ſtroke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leches ſayd playnly that there
was no hope at all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer he ſholde be heled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi.</head>
               <p>THis ſaynt Nycholas alſo knewe afore and proued full many thynges by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt.
Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o a poore woman gaue hym a certayne of floure
for almeſſe / he lefte ſome of it / and ſhe had that lytyll home in her veſſell / and
it was ſo encreaſed wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſholde oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupye it by myracle that it was moche more than euer
it was. Alſo at maſſe whan there was water brought hym and he lacked wyne / by his prayer the
water was torned in to good wyne.</p>
               <p>Alſo partryges was brought hym deer and roſted / he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded them to flee and they had
fethers and lyfe / 
<pb facs="tcp:4632:8"/>&amp; flewe forth with all as well as euer they dyd. Alſo by his prayer he made a
ſtone hole agayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge afore the crucyfyxe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yron chaynes &amp; fell vpon his heed. Alſo
by his prayer he made hole another ſtone that a grete blacke byrde lyke a kyte dyde breke / whan
there was a counſayll taken in the cloyſter of Tollentyne too make a pyt and wyte where it
myght beſt be done thrughe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers of this holy man it is ſothe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the top of a
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne rede the water ſprange vp / by the whiche token they vnderſtode playnly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there it
was beſt to dygge it. ¶ In tranſlatio ſcti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nicolai.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="translation">
            <div n="1" type="reading">
               <head>Lectio. j.</head>
               <p>ALſo this greate myracle is to be had in mynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan this pytte was in dyggynge a greate
quaue began bothe in the pytte &amp; in the foundacyon of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chyrche. And whan this blyſſed
ſaynt prayed wepyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grounde was ſad &amp; ſure / ſo that there was no fere fallynge.
Whan that this mooſt holy man ſhone with ſo grete myracles at the laſte god ordeyned to
call hym vnto hym / and whan the ende of his lyfe drawed nye he herde by nyght before matyns tyme
the mooſt ſweteſt aungelles the which abode contynually .vi. monethes before his dethe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reading">
               <head>lcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ij.</head>
               <p>THis bleſſed ſaynt Nycholas had ſo grete delyte in the herynge of them that he brennynge
for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſyre of another lyfe and ceaſed not to ſaye with ſaynt Paule I deſyre and
coueyte to be departed &amp; to be with cryſte / for than I were ſurer. And openly he ſayd
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were preſent that the tyme of his dethe was nye / the whiche h e toke with ſo
grete mekenes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocyon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they meruayled that ſtode by / namly whan they ſawe hym with
ſo grete mekenes aſkynge theym forgyuenes for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had treſpaſſed them. He wente
<pb facs="tcp:4632:9"/>with ſo grete Ioye &amp; gladnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ſene ſtonde euer by the heuenly
company of aungelles / and it was no meruayll bycauſe our ſauyoure Ieſu cryſte appered to
hym with his blyſſed mother vyrgyn / &amp; ſaynt Auſtyn his aduouryes confortynge hym &amp;
ſayenge / well thou be thou good ſeruaunt and true come in to the Ioye of thy god. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Thus endeth the lyfe of ſaynt Nycholas of Tollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne. Enprynted at London in
Fleteſtrete at the ſygne of the ſonne by Wynkyn de worde.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Wynkyn de Worde.</head>
                  <figDesc>tripartite printer's device of Wynkyn de Worde, McKerrow 23, incorporating: a sun over a
crescent moon with stars; the mark and initials of William Caxton; de Worde's name, a hunting dog
and sagittary below</figDesc>
               </figure> 
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4632:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
